I started as an analyst and I was put on
uh the Iraq desk in the office of
leadership analysis. So I was
essentially Saddam Hussein's classified
biographer. So I said, "Coper, I'm not
working on al-Qaeda." Was that for real
or was that just for their benefit? He
said, "Oh, something terrible is going
to happen." And two months later it did.
>> Whose fault was it then?
>> Well, it was the greatest intelligence
failure in American history. I was
informed that we were going to start
torturing in May of 2002. And I said,
"That's a slippery slope. It's wrong."
And they said, "Well, either you're in
or you're out." And there were CIA
officers, very senior CIA officers, who
would go to the secret prisons to watch
torture sessions just because they
wanted to enjoy the torture session.
>> Did you ever think it would cost you
your freedom? Were you ever worried
about that?
>> Never thought it would. I spent 23
months in prison. People objected that I
was not contrite. What's the difference
between somebody who orders hit teams to
go around the world and just murder
people in cold blood versus the mafia
guy who murders somebody who won't pay
back the $100,000 that he borrowed.
What's the difference? They're both
killers. My boss who I really really
liked and respected. Like you would
never guess that he was in the CIA. You
would look at him and say ambassador,
>> right? He came up to me. He gave me a
hug and he said stay safe. And then he
whispers in my ear, "And kill them all."
>> Do you think that's your mother's spy?
>> Yes.
>> For the Israelis. Yeah.
>> John, welcome. Thank you so much for
being here. I can't believe you're in
Cyprus.
>> I'm very happy since 1992.
>> What a change.
>> It's a different world. Truly good.
>> I don't recognize anything. And in fact,
I took a lot of pictures in Nicole when
I was there in '92 and don't recognize
any of the places.
>> Let's do a before and after. It's going
to be hilarious. I know. It's a big big
change.
>> Huge difference. Huge.
>> We see it. I mean, Limol's completely
transformed. It's a mini Dubai now.
>> But yeah, even some of the beautiful old
buildings, they've been knocked down and
lots of changes, but in a good way
because we need change and we need to
grow and develop. So
>> that's right.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, welcome to Cypress.
Raphael,
>> so happy to have you here with us. It's
a real real treat. And
>> um so before we go into the
>> into all the amazing details that I
think all the listeners can't wait to
hear, I want to start with talking about
your Greek heritage, like the obvious.
>> Yeah.
>> Because I do, you know, I do a lot on
Instagram, always talking about, it was
a bit like my big fat Greek wedding.
What is Greek and beautiful and
wonderful in the world? And here you are
an American CIA who's originally Greek.
So tell us a bit about your your
parents, your lineage, America.
>> All four, excuse me.
>> All four of my grandparents were from
Rodos. Um my father's parents I've been
from there.
>> Oh, I love it. My my father's parents
from Yalisos up north and my mother's
parents from Gatavia. It's the farthest
southern uh village on the island. And
you know, it's funny. We were raised to
believe we were always Rodian going
back, you know, till the beginning of
time, always rodeian.
>> And so I did a I just happened to do a
23 and me test after I was invited to
come to to Cypress to speak
>> when when uh Paul Lambis emailed me. He
said, "Hey, we want you to speak at this
uh criates of the diaspora." And I said,
"Great. I'd love to count me in, but I'm
not criate. My family is Greek. He said,
"That's okay. Come and speak and it'll
be fun."
>> I happen to do a DNA test at the same
time.
>> Don't tell me you got a criate anyway.
>> 26% criate.
>> No way. I love that. Oh my gosh.
>> Which was a shock. And I called a cousin
of mine and I said I said, "It's 26%
criate and it's all from from Papu's
side."
>> Yeah.
>> And he said, "Yeah." He said, "I told
you that." And I said, "No, you said
kiti. You said originally we came from
Kiti." And I said, "That was crazy. I'd
never heard that." He said, "No, I said
keep not."
>> So there it is.
>> Amazing. And there's a there's um a
village in Rose called Arhangelos.
>> Yes. It's heavily criate.
>> This very similar accent to the criates.
>> I'll tell you a funny story about
Arhangelos.
>> Um I like it there. It's very nice. Uh
when I was in college,
>> my cousin was getting married in Warren,
Ohio. I don't remember why I went with
her, my mother, and my grandmother that
day. I drove them all to the what do you
call it? The wedding gown store,
whatever they call it, the bridal bridal
uh boutique.
>> And there was a girl working there from
Arangelos. Her parents were from
Arangelos. And she was really
good-looking. And I said, uh, and we
were talking and smiling and flirting.
>> We were 20. I'm going to say 21 or 22.
>> And I said to my mother, I'm going to
ask her out.
>> And my Yaya says, "Oh, no, you're not."
She said, "I don't interfere, but I'm
putting my foot down on this." I said,
"Why?" And she said, "She's from from
Arangelos."
I said, "So what?
>> That's a that's a positive thing. She's
Rodian.
>> She's Rodian." And she says, "People
from Arangelos have big heads and they
lie and they care only about property."
>> That's hilarious.
>> They have big heads, like oversized
heads and they're all liars.
>> And I said, "Oh, okay."
>> Well, in that if that's the case,
>> yeah, I'm not going to piss everybody
off. So, I never asked around.
>> Oh my goodness. The one that got away.
If you're listening to this now, can you
imagine there's a lady somewhere going,
"What? What? That was him?"
>> And you know, the last time I was in
roads, it was last year. I stopped in
Arangulos with that same cousin and uh
and we had lunch and I said, "It's
fantastic here."
>> Yeah.
>> I missed the boat.
>> Oh my goodness. That is so funny. And
you did your first wife was Greek origin
as well.
>> Yeah. From from Hios.
>> From Hios. Yeah. But also second
generation like in
>> her parents were born in Hios. So she
was Yeah. She was
>> Oh, so she's like Yeah. First generation
American. Wow. And you grew up So you
grew up in a very My big fat Greek
wedding style, huh? with the Greeks.
>> I had 27 first cousins on my mother's
side.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah. It was big family. She was one of
nine
>> and then everybody had kids.
>> Yeah.
>> So, and and you and you like Greek. You
were speaking Greek at home.
>> Yeah. But you know what though? When I
went to college?
>> Uh I wanted to take Greek. I went to
George Washington University. I wanted
to take Greek and they didn't offer
Greek. The only ancient Greek.
>> Okay.
>> So, I wanted to take Greek. They said,
"Well, it's available at Georgetown
University." We had this consortium of
DC universities it was called. So I went
up there and I met with the uh the
professor who also happened to be the
dean of the school of languages and
linguistics the salatis. And um I said I
want to I want to take Greek. He said
you can't. We already started a week
earlier. You're going to be too far
behind. I said no but I I spoke Greek at
home. He said okay let's talk. So we
start talking and he says to me your
Greek is terrible. And I said, "What?
Really?"
>> He said, "You speak in this weird 1930s
era
doian slang."
>> And he said, "When did your people come
over?" I said, "Well,
>> that's when they came over.
>> 1931,
my my par my father's parents, 1934, my
my mother's." And he said, "And you're
probably from what? Roads." And I said,
"Yes."
>> He said, "You're going to have to start
at the beginner class." Oh my goodness.
>> And I said, "Okay." And since I knew,
you know, the alphabet and
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> the basic words, I I was okay. And he
let me So I studied there for three
years. And then when I went to the CIA,
um
>> I just continued taking Greek at church
on my own
>> and then was assigned later to Greece
while I was with the CIA.
>> Yeah. But you learn Arabic.
>> Yeah, I learned Arabic.
>> Oh my goodness. I mean, I'm I'm half
Lebanese and Arabic is mass my Greek is
much better than my Arabic.
>> Very very difficult. Very difficult.
>> At the end of it, I said to my
instructor, I feel like you owe me a
master's degree because I didn't work
this hard in graduate school.
>> No. Yeah. Really? It's tough. It's
really tough. How did you learn Arabic?
Because you studied Boy Middle Eastern
studies.
>> I studied Middle Eastern studies in
school, but didn't but Arabic wasn't
>> part of it. It was more like the history
and culture.
>> Okay.
>> In fact, it was a new
>> There wasn't a language part.
>> No, it was a new program. I I actually
went to the dean as a sophomore and I
said,
>> "And why why did you choose that?"
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, I was always fascinated by the
Middle East.
>> Oh, really?
>> Yeah. Well, when I was a sophomore in
high school, the Iranians took uh the
American embassy and took our diplomats
hostage and I was fascinated. So, I went
to the dean
um at GW and I said I I was one of only
four Middle Eastern studies majors and I
said, "With all due respect, you've got
a Middle Eastern studies program with no
Arabic, no oil economics, and no
religion.
What kind of program is that?"
>> Yeah. What's going on?
>> He He was not nice about it. Don't tell
me how to run my program.
>> Okay.
>> Well, now here it is, you know, 40 years
later. Is it 40? Yeah. Yeah. Actually 40
>> 40.
>> And um
>> and they have Arabic and they have Islam
and they have I actually I actually took
Islam on my own through the consortium
again. And then my senior year they
brought Sus Nasser the father of Vali
Nasser to GW. So I studied under him.
>> Wow.
>> And um
and uh oil economics finally they have a
whole program but it took them decades.
>> Yeah. because it's you know that I mean
I had also when I was studying
cross-cultural I don't know what they
called it crosscultural studies part of
my hospitality and tourism degree but
it's so important and I know my
grandfather so we're Greek Orthodox
Christians but my grandfather was
originally from HS in Syria and he was
taught Arabic by learning to recite and
memorize the Quran
>> and when he got older and he was in
business and and the Americans were
moving over to they were in the Middle
East a lot when he got um started a
construction company and it's a whole
story. But one of the things that um
apparently they attributed to his
success was he could sit at a table with
Muslims and he would know more of the
Quran than they did and he would start
reciting things to them and they would
go, "Wow." And he really bridged that
gap and was like, "We're all the same.
We can all learn together." And
>> my grandfather my grandfather dropped
out of school in the third grade to work
in the fields. One of 19 children.
>> Wow. And uh and sometimes we would be
sitting at the table and he would start
speaking Turkish and we were like babu
and he's like we had to learn these
languages and then he would speak
Italian.
>> Imagine
>> it was the craziest thing.
>> And what a gift languages is such a
gift.
>> So what happened that made you
join the CIA? How did this turn out? You
said you were fascinated as a young
>> Oh, yeah. Well, you know, because
because I was from an immigrant family.
>> I was raised with the idea that
the United States was so good to us, we
had to pay back somehow. And so, I only
considered public service. I never
considered going.
>> Isn't it amazing how immigrants often
appreciate the country so much more than
the people born into it?
>> They really, really do. And I mean, look
at the Greek community in the United
States. It's the It's the best educated
and second wealthiest immigrant
community in America.
>> Is it? What's the first?
>> The Jews.
>> Well, I just had to hear that come out
of your mouth. I was going to say it,
but yeah. And the third
>> uh the Indians.
>> Okay. Interesting.
>> Interesting. So I only considered public
service and um
>> there's public service you know there's
working in you know electricity or
something like that and then there's
CIA. It's a big gap.
>> Well I was thinking more of State
Department foreign service maybe Capitol
Hill
>> and then my adviser in graduate school
turned out to be a CIA officer
undercover as an adviser.
>> No way.
>> And uh and he spotted me and thought
that I would be good.
>> So why was he there undercover in the
first place to to spot to find
>> to find
>> Yeah. students.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah.
>> Amazing. What was anyone else hired from
your
>> No.
>> Friends? No, just you.
>> Wow. That's amazing.
>> So, how does the hiring process work?
>> Well, it's different now.
>> Yeah.
>> They changed it in 1993. Congress passed
the Equal Employment Opportunity Act.
>> Okay.
>> Very, very much less sexy.
>> You just go to www.cia.gov
and click apply.
>> Okay. So it's
>> but before they would be out scouting.
>> Oh yeah. Outlooking.
>> Yeah. Before the internet and computers
were were in widespread use. So
yeah before 911 there were 250
applicants for every position.
>> After 911 and this has held steady there
about 2500 applicants for every one open
position. So it's very very competitive
and you have to get through AI and the
computer screen. I mean, people are
patriotic.
>> They're patriotic.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Well, patriotic, I'm not I'm just
putting out
>> You're not going to apply to the CIA if
you hate the CIA. You're not going to
apply to the CIA if you hate the
government.
>> But it could also be the the the movies,
the the the perceives glamour.
>> Yeah. But I like old western movies.
Doesn't mean I want to be a cowboy.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Interesting. Okay. So, then
you started working in the CIA and then
your career progressed. Tell us about
your Yeah. because I know you were
stationed in Athens and different
places. Obviously, you learn Arabic.
>> Well, I I started as an analyst.
>> Um I was hired as an analyst and I was
put on uh the Iraq desk in the office of
leadership analysis. So, I was
essentially Saddam Hussein's classified
biographer. We worked with a team of uh
psychologists and psychiatrists to
analyze the personalities of foreign
leaders to look for weaknesses that we
could exploit.
>> Oh my god. Tell us about that.
>> Well, I was
>> tell us about Saddam Hussein. What's
your take on
>> We always We always compare Saddam to a
a mob boss.
>> You know, people people grossly over
overuse the word crazy. Oh, he's crazy.
>> The Ayatoll is crazy. Saddam's crazy.
>> Crazy is just different.
>> None of them are crazy. None of them.
>> Just because we don't like their
policies or we disagree with their style
of leadership doesn't mean they're
crazy. With Saddam, he was
extraordinarily quick to use violence.
>> And we
compared his leadership style to the
leadership style of a mob boss.
>> If you spoke out against him, he would
cut your tongue out and nail it to the
front door of your house. And that way,
nobody in the neighborhood was going to
speak out against him. if you were a
problem or or he thought you might
become a problem politically in the
future, he would either kill you or
exile you. If you were, for example, a
popular general, let's say you had
commanded successful troops against the
Iranians, you're not going to get
promoted. You're going to be made
ambassador to the Philippines. So,
you're so far away, you can't possibly
challenge him. There's a famous video,
it's it's freely available on YouTube
from the day that Saddam took power.
He's at a he's in a small theater on
stage and all the generals who had
helped him come to power that day are
sitting there in the audience, dozens of
them. And he says, he's sitting on the
stage, he's smoking a cigar, and his
brother Barzan Titi is down there
standing amongst the generals. And
Saddam says, "We uncovered a plot, a
plot against the revolution, and it's
among the generals." And there's, you
know, rumbling.
And then he says, "General Muhammad,
you've been caught." And General
Muhammad stands up and he says, "Mr.
President, I'm innocent. I I support
you. I love you." Barzon grabs him,
takes him out, and you hear a gunshot in
the background. And he does it to a
second general and a third general and a
fourth general. Finally, he names the
next guy and he jumps up and tried to
save himself. Says, "Yes, I confess. I
did it. I did it." Well, there was never
any plot and they killed him. Killed
about a dozen of them that day. And it
so frightened all the rest. It so cowed
them that nobody dared to challenge
Saddam.
>> That's when people say it's crazy. I
mean, this is crazy. But it's not crazy.
It's ruthless.
>> It's ruthless,
>> but it's not crazy.
>> It's just so different from anything
that we're
>> brought up to believe what is right,
what is correct, what
>> is the norm in,
>> you know, it's like the colloquial use
of the term nervous breakdown.
>> There's no such thing as a nervous
breakdown. That's not a medical term.
It's not a psychiatric term. It's just a
term that we've come up with, the media
have come up with that we attribute to
people who, you know, are in some kind
of a mental health
>> psychosis or Yeah. mental health.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow.
That's Yeah.
Again, we go back to that's crazy.
>> Um, so you were studying
um and and looking after that side and
then you were moved to Athens. Well,
years later.
>> Years later. So, what happened?
>> So, I was an analyst for seven and a
half years. I served overseas in Bahrain
as an analyst. Um, served in Saudi
Arabia, in Kuwait.
>> And you were undercover whenever you
were serving.
>> Well, you have to be. You can't just go
to the airport and say, "I'm with the
CIA."
>> So, um, I switched to operd. He loved
what you were doing.
>> Oh, I loved it. Yeah.
>> So, I switched to operations in 1997.
went through the operations training and
then went to Greece as a
counterterrorism officer.
>> Spent two years there back to
headquarters
for a year almost a year is that right?
>> No almost two years and a half and then
uh went to Pakistan as the head of
counterterrorism operations.
>> And how did you find it? because we all
watch the movies and
>> but you know we don't know h how do you
find it living that double life
>> like
>> no problem h
>> how does how does that work because
>> but you know what though we all live
double lives we all have
>> we go to work we smile we and then we go
home and
>> sure now if you're just some guy I'm
sitting next to on a plane and you ask
me
>> but you're you're going to work and
you're playing someone that's not you
let's say I might have parts of you
>> what makes you think it's not me
>> yeah That's what I'm asking. That's what
I'm asking.
>> No, but you're saying it's two different
lives and I'm saying no, it's not.
>> It's not.
>> No.
>> No, it's not two different lives.
>> Okay.
>> If if you're
>> Explain that. Explain that further.
>> I mean, for all of us, because we're not
in this, the listeners, myself, we're
not in this world. So, this is something
so alien to us. So, let us into your
world. Describe it. If you're just some
guy I'm sitting next to on a plane and
you ask what I do for a living,
>> I'm going to tell you a lie.
>> And I'm gonna the lie is going to sound
the li Well, the lie is going to sound
so boring that you're not going to ask
me a follow-up question.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm going to say I'm involved in
training in trade negotiations
>> and you're going to say, "Oh, that
sounds so interesting." And you're lying
and it doesn't and you're not going to
ask me a follow-up.
>> That's it.
>> So, it's not really so much a double
life.
like the movies.
>> Yeah.
>> And then but then when you're on the
ground,
>> what
>> tell us about it. This is this such a
different world. So, okay, you're on the
ground and you're going about your your
daily life pretending that you're in
trading.
>> No, no, no, no, no, no,
>> no. That's called That's called a
throwaway cover.
>> Okay.
>> That's just something that I just say
just to get you to shut up.
>> Okay. Um, there are different kinds of
cover.
>> Uh, there's what's called integrated
cover, in which case I would work a
normal 8 hour day doing a cover job and
then at night I would go out and do my
CIA job.
>> I was never under integrated cover.
>> Okay.
>> Um, I was under
well, no, I shouldn't say what I was
under. I was under the kind of cover
that I was a CIA officer all day.
>> Okay. and I was working with that
country's intelligence service.
>> So I was known to them as John the CIA
officer.
>> And so I would go over to
whatever the intelligence service was,
the Greeks, the, you know, this one,
that one, the other one, and trade
information. We would do operations
jointly.
>> Yeah. Just go about my business.
>> Amazing. Okay. So let's go through now.
We're still going to the part you went
moved to Athens,
>> right? So I moved to Athens in 1998
and um my job there well when I
originally applied for it, it was to
work against the Greek terrorist group
uh 17 November revolutionary
organization 17 November. And there was
another one called the popular
revolutionary struggle.
>> Mhm.
>> And um as well as the Abu Nidal
organization, the Libyans, the PFLP, the
PFLPGC, the DFLP, whatever groups happen
to pop up, Islamic Jihad, they they
didn't have very much of a presence.
Whatever groups there were that meant
harm to Americans,
>> that was the job. Once I got there, 90%
of it was 17 November. the Arabs,
>> which you weren't expecting.
>> I didn't expect it to be 90%.
>> But but it it was the Arabs. I mean, by
then, we've got the immediate aftermath
of the Oslo Accords
>> and everybody's getting along.
I didn't have to worry about the Arabs.
The Libyans, you know, changed their
policy. They weren't making trouble
anymore.
>> It was all about 17 November.
>> Yeah. So interesting. And you stayed in
Athens for a couple of years.
>> Uhhuh. Two years. And then
>> was it a dangerous time then?
>> The most dangerous time in my career.
>> Really?
>> Yeah. I was in far more danger in Athens
than I was in Pakistan,
>> which I think people wouldn't put that
together.
>> Most people don't know that in that
period from the mid 1970s until 2002,
the US spent more money on security in
Athens than we spent in Beirut. It was
far more dangerous in it was
unbelievable and me coming from Beirut
like I know that that was you know yeah
a crazy place and we used to go to
Athens and feel safe and you know more
okay it wasn't we didn't have the
European Union then but it was you know
we felt like yeah
>> was Europe and more civilized
>> but you had this group that not only had
nobody ever been caught nobody had ever
been identified
>> so is it the guy you're sitting next to
is it the guy in traffic is it the guy
on the motorcycle weaving through
traffic and coming up alongside you.
>> You just didn't know.
>> That's amazing.
Okay. And after Athens,
>> I went back to headquarters in August of
and almost immediately turned around and
went back to the United Arab Emirates. I
was there until
I was I was assigned to something called
the 17 November task force, but because
of my Arabic, I was constantly on loan
to other groups.
>> And so I spent much of that time in Abu
Dhabi,
did some work in Beirut, and um and then
911 hit
>> and then everybody everything changed.
Everybody was volunteering to go.
>> Tell us about 911.
>> What a terrible day.
>> I mean, I Everyone in the world will
remember where they were on 911.
>> Everyone in the world. I had a meeting
scheduled that morning for 9:00 with
Condisa Rice. She was the national
security adviser at the time. I was
going with the director of the
counterterrorism center, Kofer Black,
later ambassador Kofer Black. And um
I walked over to Kofheer's office to
tell him that the car was ready to take
us to the White House. And when I got
there, when I got to his office, I was
across the hall. So I I got to his
office and these were the days before
you could watch TV on a computer. So his
secretary had a very small TV on her
desk and she had it on and one of the
towers of the World Trade Center was
burning. I said, 'What happened to the
World Trade Center? And she said, 'A
plane flew into it.' And I said, 'You
know what? That happened once before in
1930.
A a plane flew into the Empire State
Building, but it was really foggy and
rainy. It's so crystal clear today. How
can you not see that you're flying into
the World Trade Center?
>> And just as I said the words, the second
plane flew in. And she turned around and
she said to me, "Did you see that or did
I imagine it?" I ran back to the office
and I said, "Guys, we're under attack.
Two planes just uh hit both towers of
the World Trade Center." We all ran back
up to Kofheer's office
that there were TVs hanging from the
ceiling.
>> One was, you know, BBC, CNN, Canel, the
Russians, the Chinese, the
>> and all of them were on and all of them
were showing the World Trade Center. And
um
must have been 150 of us gathered there.
And finally,
somebody behind me shouted, "Will
somebody please lead and then Kofer, it
was like slapping him in the face." He
said, "Yes, you go to the director's
office and tell him this. You go to
security. You go to operations."
And we just stood there and watched, you
know, watched the towers burn. And then
the Pentagon was hit.
>> And then somebody said, "There's still a
plane in the air."
>> The the vice president ordered that jets
be scrambled to shoot it down. it. The
passengers brought it down before it
could be shot. And um
and then Kofheer stood on his desk or on
the secretary's desk and uh and said,
"Today we're at war.
All of us are going to have to fight.
Not all of us are going to come home.
If you want to leave now, no one will
think less of you." And nobody budged.
Finally, the CIA has its own internal
police force called the ESPOS, the
special protective officers. And ASPO
had already come in and said, "Everybody
evacuate." Nobody budged. Came back in
45 minutes later. He said, "If you don't
evacuate, you'll be arrested."
So, we started evacuating. It took me
two hours just to get out of my parking
space.
And then,
>> wow.
>> I lived,
>> you know, it's not really evacuating, is
it? I mean
>> I mean it's the place isn't designed for
tens of thousands of people to all leave
at exactly the same time. So
>> um I lived exactly 10 km from
headquarters. I got 5 kilometers home 5
km toward home
>> and I I had to uh abandon my car on the
side of the highway. It was like World
War Z like nothing could move. So, I
walked the five kilometers
and I saw when I when I got to the the
Theodore Roosevelt Bridge where I would
make a right to go home, I saw the
deputy national security adviser coming
across the bridge and he had no shoes.
And I remember thinking, you're supposed
to be protecting us. You're supposed to
be commanding the response to this and
you ran away with no shoes.
like how did how did this happen? So I
got to my apartment. My girlfriend, who
later became my wife, she was also a
senior CIA officer. She met me there
about an hour later. We went to the roof
of my building. We watched the Pentagon
burn for a little while. And then I
said, "We should give blood or
something." So we went we went back
downstairs. We tried to donate blood,
but the line was 24 hours long.
>> And then finally, I said, "This is
ridiculous. We need to get back to
work." So I walked the five kilometers
back to my car, drove across the grassy
median and then went back to
headquarters and I stayed there for the
next four days. I just slept under my
desk. Everybody did that.
>> And you know, America had never seen
anything like it. It's not like Europe
where terrorist attack in history of
wars or you know America's
>> recent history
>> almost double the number of deaths um
compared to Pearl Harbor which had been
the worst attack in American history.
>> Yeah, it was bad.
>> And what's your take on 9/11 if you can
say?
>> It's very straightforward.
>> Al-Qaeda did it. They told us they were
going to
>> There's a lot of conspiracy theories.
[__] the conspiracy theories.
>> Whether it was the the Jews or the
Saudis or the Bush family or the space
aliens or the lizard people. I've heard
it all.
>> Oh my god. I haven't heard the last two.
>> I've heard it all, including the last
two. And people tell me I'm an idiot and
a fool.
Al-Qaeda had been planning that attack
since 1996.
We watched them plan it. We listened to
them plan it. We disrupted it a couple
of times
>> because they only had to be lucky once.
We had to be right on every single time.
>> So, they kept on trying
>> and you had managed a few times, but
that time you missed it.
>> Mhm. On July the 6th, I was entertaining
a group of intelligence officers from
the Middle East, and we did this
literally every single day. You'd have a
group come from whatever country and you
give them a full day of briefings and
then you exchange gifts and then you
take them for a photo op with the
director and then at night you take them
to a very expensive restaurant and then
you do it again the next day with
another group. So that day July the 6th
I had this group from the Middle East
and um I scheduled the full day of
briefings for them. One of the briefings
was on al-Qaeda and it was with a young
25-year-old junior analyst just come in
and give us the the basics on al-Qaeda.
And so instead of him coming, Ambassador
Black came with the chief of operations
for the Osama bin Laden group. And I I
was so surprised. I said, "Oh,
gentlemen." I stood up. I said,
"Gentlemen, this is Ambassador Kofheer
Black, the director of counterterrorism,
and this is the director of operations."
And Kofheer sat down and said, he looked
right at them and he said, "Something
terrible is going to happen. We don't
know exactly where or when, but it's
going to be a an attack on an
unprecedented scale." He said, "The
chatter that we're picking up
is
camp commanders
on the phone with their students and
they're crying and saying, "I'll see you
in paradise." They're saying code words
for a massive attack. The honey salesman
is coming with vast quantities of honey.
There's going to be a gigantic football
match, a huge wedding. They're all code
words for an attack. He said, "I'm
begging you if you have any sources
inside al-Qaeda.
>> Please help us."
>> Neutralize them.
>> And they just sat there. So, at the end
of the day, I sent them back to the
hotel. I said, "I I'll pick you up in 3
hours for dinner." And I went to his
office to thank him for taking the time
to do the briefing. The guy's in charge
of counterterrorism for the entire
world.
>> So, he's busy. So I said, "Coper, I'm
not working on al-Qaeda." Was that for
real
>> or was that just for their benefit? He
said, "Oh, something terrible is going
to happen." And two months later, it
did.
>> So who whose fault was it then?
>> Well, it was the greatest intelligence
failure in American history. The CIA
didn't do its job because we hadn't
recruited any sources inside al-Qaeda.
The State Department do it didn't do its
job because it gave visas to every one
of those hijackers. The FBI didn't do
its job because because they knew that
the hijackers were in the United States
and didn't tell the CIA. Congress didn't
do its job because hadn't appropriated
enough money for counterterrorism or
allowed the CIA to hire enough people.
Everybody failed. the the predecessors
of TSA didn't do their job because they
let
19 terrorists on the planes with box
cutters and they didn't catch a single
one of them. So, everybody failed.
>> An absolute tragedy. It's still shocking
to think about.
>> Terrible.
>> We witnessed it.
>> 3,000 people were killed that day.
>> Bin Laden later said that he wanted to
um destroy the American economy. You
know, I remember reading an op-ed the
next day in the Miami Herald, and it was
one of the most heart-wrenching
op-eds I had ever written. The guy was
saying, "My God, do you realize what
you've done? Do you have any idea how
many people are going to be killed now?
We killed 2 million Muslims in the 20
years after 9/11 between Afghanistan,
Iraq and you know associated operations
Libya, Syria, Somalia, Pakistan, 2
million people that would be alive
today. Like what did he think was going
to happen?
I never understood the decision-m.
>> It's so so so sad.
And when did you leave the CIA?
>> Uh in uh March of 2004.
>> Okay. So it's quite a quite a while ago.
And what made you leave?
>> I was newly divorced. My my children
were young at the time. They were let me
think
they were nine and six.
My ex-wife moved back to Ohio. And you
know, boys especially need their father
at that age.
>> And so I had a job offer from uh from
Deote uh one of the big four
>> professional services firms and they
said, "We don't care where you're
sitting, you know, when you're writing
your reports. You can work from
Starbucks. We don't care."
>> So I took that job funny for exactly
double what I was making at the CIA. And
um and I did that for the next four
years.
And so when when did you have that
moment where you said if I stay silent I
can't live with myself like I I need to
>> well you it it came incrementally.
>> Okay.
>> So
so we started torturing up was a beta in
uh on August the 2nd 2002.
>> And I thought this was wrong wrong.
And I said something internally
um at my produ at my uh promotion panel
meeting.
The new director of counterterrorism
said that I had I had uh displayed a
shocking lack of commitment to
counterterrorism
because I wouldn't be trained in the
torture techniques and I had objected to
them.
>> Wow.
>> Internally. And then there's a Greek
American guy. He's a brigadier general
in the army. He's a psychiatrist and we
were working together in the
counterterrorism center. good guy. And
he said to me, "Buddy, you know they
call you the human rights guy behind
your back." And I said, "I know. I've
heard it."
>> He said, "You know that's not a
compliment, right?"
>> And I said, "Steve, I am on the right
side of this and they are not."
>> It's as simple as that.
>> Was that the first time you saw
>> or you heard of
torture or was it something that you
knew was going on, but you hadn't been
directly involved in? Well, I was I was
informed that we were going to start
torturing in May of 2002,
and I said, "That's a slippery slope.
It's wrong."
>> Mhm.
>> And they said, "Well, either you're in
or you're out." I said, "I'm out, but I
think you're all making a terrible
mistake."
>> So, then they started torturing him on
August the 2nd.
>> And was it several types of torture or
>> Well, there were 10 techniques.
Um, but then there were others that were
not approved by the Justice Department
that they did anyway. You know,
everything from a smack in the face to
water boarding and sleep deprivation.
And
>> I I've seen a picture of um I think it
was in Korea. I think it must be quite a
famous picture of um different soldiers
waterboarding
someone I think from North Korea. And I
think the part that I found most
disturbing was that the soldiers were
smiling
>> while doing it
>> just like Abu Grape.
>> And I think that's something that people
end up this you know sadistic.
>> Yeah. There's a group thing
>> horrible side.
>> Yeah. comes out and and people get this
I don't know devilish
and I say that not in a a nice way that
you would for children just horrible
mean
inhumane side that comes out that feels
joy.
>> Yeah.
>> And that must be really scary to see
that in someone you know or someone you
had thought you previously liked.
>> It's terrible. I mean these are people
these are people that I consider to be
my friends.
>> Yeah. Our kids socialize together, our
wives socialized, and then all of a
sudden
>> they go to work and murder people or
torture people and then they go home at
the end of the day and everything's
normal.
>> That's worrying. I mean, that's that's
psychopathic behavior for me.
>> Yeah. That's what I considered it to be.
>> That's when you say that person's crazy.
>> Yeah.
>> In some form.
>> Yes.
So, so when did when did you Okay, so
you started saying that and you weren't
happy with it.
>> Well, and I assumed somebody was going
to say something. Somebody was going to
be
>> so upset that they were going to leak
this to the media and it never happened
>> and then in 2007 December
>> and the results that you wanted came or
didn't come via this technique. Of
course, it doesn't it doesn't work.
>> Yeah, it doesn't work. No, I know you've
said that before over and over again.
doesn't work.
>> And so it wasn't leaked. And then
>> and then in December of 2007, I got a
call from a reporter at ABC News in New
York and he said that he had a source
who said that I had tortured Abu Zuba.
He said that was absolutely untrue. I
was the only person who was kind to Abu
Zuba.
>> Maybe that maybe that source was there
to make you speak. Maybe that was
someone's way of getting it back to you.
No,
>> that's really that's a very nice
>> way to analyze it. No. No. No.
>> So, so why would they have called you?
Where did that leak come?
>> Because word had gotten out
>> and they needed somebody to blame. They
didn't want to go to prison.
So, blame the guy who was a thorn in
their side from the beginning.
>> From the beginning. Maybe they blamed
you for the word getting out in the
first place.
>> No.
>> No. Also,
>> no. Uh they blamed the Guantanamo
defense attorneys.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. So then the reporter called you
>> and uh I decided to make a long story
short, I decided to
>> just tell the truth.
>> No.
>> And that's what I did.
>> And then then
>> then the investigation started. So the
FBI investigated me from December of
2007 to December of 2008. And then they
decided
>> It's a long time.
>> Oh, no. It's not.
>> It's not. No,
>> it didn't feel like a long time.
>> No.
>> I did. I hadn't done anything wrong.
>> You weren't worried at that stage. You
weren't
>> You just stood by your principles, your
morals,
>> and said, "This is the right thing to
do."
>> Mhm.
>> Okay. That's amazing.
>> And then in December 2008, they dropped
the investigation. They sent my
attorneys a letter saying that they had
found no evidence of a crime.
>> Okay.
>> Done. Then a few weeks later, Barack
Obama becomes president and he names
John Brennan as the deputy national
security adviser. Brennan then secretly
asked the Justice Department to reopen
the case against me. I had no idea. So
they started
>> and again why like why you why
what happened there?
>> They needed somebody to blame. M
>> so why not blame the one person who was
the thorn in your side
that's what they did
>> but at the end of the day they couldn't
get you for torturing because you didn't
do it
>> no they never charged you with torturing
>> exactly so I mean they're blaming but
they're blaming it's almost like a
scapegoat for something else we're
talking about torture and these people
who've done it which is illegal
>> it wasn't illegal
>> it's it's whole point.
>> That was the whole point. I said it was
illegal. I believed it was illegal. I
still think it's illegal. Ethics are a
separate issue.
>> Yeah.
>> That doesn't come into the debate.
>> So, it wasn't illegal. Although you said
that there were certain ones that were
okay and they used others that were not
okay. Those are illegal.
>> Well, that's illegal.
>> Yeah.
>> But that's going to be just sort of lost
in the scrum.
>> Okay.
>> The US has a law called the Federal
Torture Act of 1946. Mhm.
>> that specifically outlaws exactly the
tech the techniques that we used. Okay.
In the
1960s,
we ratified the United Nations
Convention Against Torture and Inhumane
Treatment. We wrote it and ratified it.
So, these techniques are clearly
illegal.
But then,
you know, I'll add, we executed Japanese
soldiers who had waterboarded American
prisoners of war in 1946. In 1968, an
American soldier waterboarded a North
Vietnamese prisoner and was sent to
prison for 20 years for waterboarding.
And then in 2002, the Justice Department
said, "Well,
no, it's not it's not illegal." Well, of
course it was illegal, but they said it
wasn't. Which then covered the
torturers.
>> The torturers could say, "Well, the
Justice Department said it was legal, so
you can't prosecute us. We only followed
orders
>> and and the law said that we could do
it."
>> I just find it scary because this is
war. Even in a prison, even I mean,
these are all, okay, of course,
anti-terrorism.
>> You know what though? It wasn't war.
There was no congressional declaration
of war against anybody.
>> I just find it so frightening in war in
prisons in how people can be so mean
when you give them they say give a man
power and you'll see who he is.
>> How I mean it's it's just absolutely
insane when you think how someone can
turn and treat another human being as if
they're an animal and they get joy from
it.
>> Yes. That's what that's what for me
scares me.
>> And there were CIA officers, very senior
CIA officers who would go to the secret
prisons to watch torture sessions just
because they wanted to enjoy the torture
session,
not because they had any anything to
contribute to, you know, an intelligence
operation.
>> That that must have been the point where
you just said, I'm I've just got nothing
to do with these people. I'm I'm
>> I was done. I was ready to leave. The
whole place changed on 911. I was ready
to go.
which is sad because you'd loved it so
much and you felt you were you know
doing something good for your country
and
>> and I I I heard a quote that was it your
um your senior that said um
>> yeah that you were one of the best that
he'd had under under him and how well
you were doing and
>> um
>> did you ever think it would cost you
your freedom? Were you ever worried
about that?
>> Never thought it would.
>> No.
No. And I I took a lot of criticism when
I got out of prison. I spent 23 months
in prison. But when I got out,
uh people objected that I was not
contrite. And I said, I will never ever
apologize.
>> Never. I'm right. They're wrong. The
world is going to come around to my side
of the of the story. And it has.
>> So, no. I I gave this interview to the
BBC. What was it called? Uh Hard Talk,
famous BBC interview show. And it's
famously
um
difficult.
And finally the interviewer
said uh with great frustration, "Well,
you've not apologized a single time
since you got on this show. You've never
apologized." I said, "I will never
apologize for anything. never.
>> They should be apologizing to the
American people.
And now here we are.
>> What an interview as well to get to
where where they want the conversation
to go and direct.
>> And he's so frustrated that I just
wouldn't play along. And I said, "No."
And now my detractors are either dead or
they're retired
>> and people have come around to my point
of view.
>> How does that feel knowing that people
>> vindicating?
>> Yeah. Mhm.
>> Must be.
>> Yeah.
>> So, there was never a time you regretted
telling the truth. You stand by it until
now.
>> 100%.
>> Tell us about 23 months in prison.
That's not a It's not a little amount of
time. That's the way you've got five
kids, you know?
>> That was the hardest part. It was more
Groundhog Day than anything else. It was
just the same day repeating itself over
and over and over for 23 months. So, you
read a lot. the exercise a lot. I wrote
a book in longhand, okay, that ended up
doing very well. Um,
yeah, and just stand by your beliefs.
>> What did prison teach you that was
completely different to the CIA
teachings? Like, I mean, it's night and
day experiences.
>> You know, I dealt with psychopaths at
the CIA and I dealt with different
psychopaths in prison.
wasn't really very different. Some of
them had high educations and others
didn't
and found themselves, you know, on
different sides of the law.
What's the difference between somebody
who orders hit teams to go around the
world to just murder people in cold
blood versus the mafia guy who murders
somebody who won't pay back the $100,000
that he borrowed? What's the difference?
They're both killers.
A friend of mine posted something on
Facebook the other day. He said his
brother-in-law had just gotten out of
prison and he had done 20 years for
murder. So, it was the first time that
they had met. And he said, "I can't
believe I know a murderer." And I said,
"Try working at the CIA for 15 years.
Try being the only guy in the room who's
not a murderer and then then see what
kind of post-traumatic stress disorder
you have."
>> That's insane. Do you think you have
post-traumatic stress from it? No. In
fact, a therapist friend of mine said to
me that he thought it was amazing that I
did have Yeah.
>> Yeah. You've come out of it. Like, you
must have a very strong mindset.
>> Yeah. My divorce was my divorce took a
far greater toll on me than than prison
ever did.
>> That's amazing to hear that. They say
actually it's divorce, death, and moving
house are the three most stressful
things you can do in your life.
>> Uhhuh. Yeah,
>> with changing jobs just behind.
>> Imagine. So, prison is under that.
>> Oh my goodness. That's hilarious.
>> So, do you think that who who paid the
bigger price for your decision to tell
the truth? Do you think it was you or
your family?
>> Oh, definitely me. Definitely me.
>> Yeah, that's an easy one.
>> But your kids didn't see you, did they?
They didn't have a daddy around for 23
months.
>> 23 months. They came they came, you
know, all the time to visit.
>> Okay.
>> But no. Yeah. 23 months.
>> How did they find that? How did you find
it sitting in prison seeing, you know,
your they're your babies, you know, how
old they are. I
>> What are you going to do? You going to
dwell on it and sit there and say, "Oh,
wo is me. My poor situation?" No, of
course not. You're going to tough it
out.
>> Yeah. That's amazing. Wow. I think we
can all learn a lot from that. Well,
really, really inspirational. Um
so um exposing the torture programs um
do you think that fear can make good
people do evil things or do you think
they've got the evil side in them?
>> I think you have to have it in you but
there's a lot to be said about group
think too.
>> You know you're in this group of people.
you've all gone through the shared
trauma and you've got to figure out a
way to respond to the trauma and
somebody says, "We should get rough with
these guys." And then everybody just
nods, "Yes, we should get rough with
these guys." And then one thing leads to
the next to the next to the next. Next
thing you know, you have a torture
program, you have a secret prison
program, you have an international
kidnapping program,
>> and they feel like they're in a group.
They're all in together. They're teaming
up. and they've convinced themselves
that they're the good guys and they're
doing this for the country to make the
country safe
>> and there's no roadblock. There's
nothing to stop them
>> and they feel powerful.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah. And connected.
>> When I was getting ready to leave for
the airport to go to to Pakistan,
um my boss who I really really liked and
respected, very elegant man, like you
would never guess that he was in the
CIA. You would look at him and say
ambassador,
>> right? He came up to me. He gave me a
hug and he said, "Stay safe." And then
he whispers in my ear, "And kill them
all." And I said, "Really, John? We've
gotten there already."
>> But even he meant it.
>> Did anyone in the CIA secretly support
you or open?
>> Lots and lots of people supported me
openly. Quite openly. 77 of them signed
a letter to the president asking him to
pardon me. Um, but even the day after my
arrest, I got a I got an email from the
former deputy director of the CIA and he
said, "You've chosen a difficult road.
I'm glad somebody did. I just wish I had
had the courage to do it myself."
>> Wow.
>> I saved it.
>> Wow. Yeah.
>> That's really
incredible.
>> It was things like that that kept me
going.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I'm sure you Yeah, you
needed a lot of it.
So
on that note of needing to yeah keep
keep going. What was the loneliest
moment in that whole experience?
>> What was the loneliest moment? I was
walking around
I was I was in prison in central
Pennsylvania
and it was very very cold and snowy. I
mean, snow passed your knee.
>> And so the yard, the track around the
the yard was closed because there was
just too much snow. So if you wanted to
go outside in these ridiculous
cold temperatures,
>> um you could walk around the basketball
court.
>> And I had been there just a couple of
weeks and I was walking with with a
mafia, Don, the boss of a family of one
of the five families in New York. And he
said to me, "How much time do you have?"
And I said, "30 months. Feels like 30
years." I ended up with 23 months. I
said, "It feels like 30 years." And he
stops. He said, "Let me give you some
advice. When somebody asks you how long
you have, you tell them five years
because if these guys hear that you have
a sentence that's so short,
they're going to kick your ass." Uh
>> he said there's a lot of jealousy and
there are a lot of guys here doing 10 20
50 years.
So I said okay. So I didn't tell anybody
that I only had 23 months.
>> Um then one day
>> So if someone asks you, you just say
five years.
>> Five years.
>> Five years. Mhm.
>> So, one day, um, well, every day at 4:00
they post,
uh, they post a schedule called the call
out list, and it'll have a prisoner's
name and number, an office that you have
to report to the next day, and the time.
So, it'll be like you have to go to the
dentist or the doctor or personnel or
whatever. It's just the list of
appointments. And one day mine was on
there and it said R&D um receiving and
discharge. That's when you're going
home.
And one of the Nazis stopped me and he
said, "Why are you on the R&D list for
tomorrow?" I said, "How the heck am I
supposed to know why I'm on the What do
you think I run the prison?"
>> That's how you have to respond.
>> Yeah.
>> But I didn't tell anybody. I'm going
home tomorrow.
>> Not a word. Except the Italians. The
Italians knew. They were my closest
friends.
>> Did you keep in touch with anyone?
>> I keep in touch with most of them.
>> Oh, really? That's so funny.
>> You know, it's crazy. You You see movies
like The Godfather and Good Fellas and
Donnie Brasco
>> and then
those guys are in your prison like the
actual guys and they become your closest
friends. I gained 35 pounds in uh what
is 35 pounds? It's like uh 15 kilos.
Okay. In prison
>> because you remember the scene in in
Good Fellas where they're cooking and
cutting the the
>> the potatoes or whatever.
>> No, the garlic. Yeah. That's how we ate
every day. We had a crooked guard on
payroll and he would bring in the pork
loin and the pasta and the marsala
sauce, the white wine for the marsala
sauce and he would bring all this food
and we would cook and cook and cook and
I I gained 35 pounds.
It was it was good. They were good guys.
I'm still in touch with all of them.
>> It's amazing, isn't it?
>> So, um
I ask every everyone on um on on my
podcast, usually on the other one, Hotel
Talk, for a favorite quote. Do you have
a favorite quote?
>> Yeah. The arc of history is long, but it
bends toward justice.
That's my favorite quote.
>> I love that. Martin Luther King.
>> And since coming out, you've done so
many things. Your life is full and busy.
>> Yeah.
>> What's for the future?
>> Well, about 10 weeks ago,
after having told some of these same
stories for the last 19 years,
I went crazy on TikTok. I don't know
why.
It's just one of those things that where
the algorithm just
>> picks you up.
>> Got me. And
>> yeah,
>> so I've been signed by the largest
talent agency in the world and my ninth
book comes out in July
and I'm going to start uh my first ever
novel. I'm working with a major
Hollywood studio on a television series.
Now I have my own podcast. Um I'm in
between podcasts. We're starting it in a
couple of weeks. On YouTube, it's it's
real John
>> Kuryaku.
>> Mhm.
>> And uh yeah, things are good. It's
almost that there aren't enough hours in
the day.
>> I love that. Well, you deserve it.
>> Thank you.
>> Um I couldn't see you and not not talk
about the big Maybe that's why I said
Tik Tok's gone mad. So, I mean the big
topic of today, Epstein.
>> Yeah.
>> What's your take on that?
>> They're all corrupt animals.
You know, these rich these rich and
powerful, they're all corrupt animals.
And the most sickening thing is that
literally nobody will face justice.
Nobody.
>> No one. You don't think it will ever.
>> There are statutes of limitations. And
and this is not a partisan issue. Donald
Trump didn't prosecute anybody. Joe
Biden didn't prosecute anybody. Barack
Obama didn't prosecute anybody. They're
all in on it.
>> All too powerful. I mean it's sure
>> you know now I think everyone in the
world even remember people who didn't
believe in any conspiracy theories I was
one now I'm like I believe anything's
possible
>> I mean the more we see the more that
comes out it's just absolutely
frightening
>> yeah I agree sickening
>> it's sickening and frightening
>> and you know there might be something to
these allegations that this Iran war
started just to distract the American
people from the Epstein files the the
vote in Congress to release the Epstein
files to mandate release of the Epstein
files was 419 to1 in the House of
Representatives and 99 to nothing in the
Senate
>> and they haven't done it.
>> Yeah. And the president said, "What are
you going to do about it? What are you
going to sue me?
So, we're all screwed."
>> Do you think they'll ever come out?
>> No.
>> There's too many powerful people
>> in the background.
>> Yes.
Do you think that was a spy?
>> Yes, for the Israelis.
>> I feel very strongly about that.
>> Like
>> we know from the release of the last
trunch of documents that he was also at
least trying to work for the CIA and the
FBI for MI5 and MI6,
>> maybe for the Germans, and that he had
actively sought a one-on-one meeting
with Putin. We don't know why, but the
Israelis 100%. Yes.
Yeah.
Right. I'm gonna on that note, I'm going
to my Instagram where I always ask
people that they can ask anything
anything they want um before I go go
live. So, oh my goodness. Oh my
goodness.
How long do we have? Okay.
So, Emma
has asked um given the rise of social
media and now the commonplace hacking
leading to loss of data combined with a
rising pessimism about democracy and a
rising interest in autocracy and
fascism.
>> Do the American people even care about
their data and privacy today?
>> No, they don't. I hate to say that.
That's so interesting.
>> But no, they don't. That's a great
question. So, you know, Congress made
such a big deal a year ago about Tik Tok
being somehow controlled by the Chinese.
It's not,
>> but somehow controlled by the Chinese
and we're going to shut down Tik Tok or
we're going to force the sale of Tik
Tok.
First of all,
they're collecting our metadata.
Who cares?
Who cares if the let's say it is owned
by the Chinese, which it's not.
Who cares if the Chinese know that I lay
in bed at night and I scroll through
videos of, you know,
>> cats or something.
>> Yeah. Little kids cooking cooking meals,
cats, whatever, police chases. Who
cares? Secondly, what in the world makes
Tik Tok's collection of metadata any
different from Facebook or Instagram or
or X or anything else?
>> Yeah. Well, I've always said that as
well. People always like, "Oh, the
phone." And I'm like, "Well, I'm quite
open anyway." And I'm like, "So, what if
someone, you know, I mean, I tell
everyone I'm vegan anyway. So, if
they're seeing that I'm scrolling vegan
recipes, it's not that's not a shock."
Yeah. Exactly. you know, or my birthday
or my real age. I'm quite happy to share
it.
>> The second part of that question, I
think, is very important, too. Americans
do have an appetite for
authoritarianism, and it scares the hell
out of me. Yeah, it really does.
>> It's not good. It weakens our democracy.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I think that's becoming more
and more apparent with everything going
on in the world.
>> Yeah. So, um,
oh my goodness, another one. Jill,
everyone wrote really long questions for
you. So, okay. Okay, you have time.
Yeah.
Let's see. What are we going for? Okay,
we'll give it a couple more minutes. So,
um, so what um gives you
hope for a better future? How do you
think we can move forward in a more
positive direction and better balance
protecting people from bad actors v
intrusion into their privacy? How would
he like to see the CIA change? Is he
more worried about the powers the CIA
has or the power of the big tech
companies?
>> Oh, let me answer up to there.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> I'm on record as saying I think the CIA
should be dismantled. I really do. Wow.
And that's a that's a body that he works
for and you love and
>> but it's not we can't trust the CIA to
not spy on Americans, which it's
forbidden by law from doing and it does
anyway. And then again just says, "What
are you going to do about it?" Um, we
can't trust our congressional
overseers, the elected officials who are
on the oversight committees for the
intelligence services. All they are are
cheerleaders. They're not overseers.
And so if they're not going to protect
our rights, then that means nobody is
going to protect our rights. And so we
shouldn't have an organization that
willfully violates our rights in the
first place. But what gives me hope is
that somebody like Ed Snowden would go
public with these revelations. And even
though he went public 13 years ago next
month and we have not seen changes,
every two years when the Patriot Act
comes back up for re reauthorization or
section 702 of the uh the Foreign
Intelligence Surveillance Act comes up,
a few more members of Congress switch
sides and oppose it. So eventually we're
going to get there and we're going to
get our civil liberties back.
>> You think? eventually.
>> Let's hope.
Um,
oh my god, I'll stop at that because
this is from Jill and there's like 20
questions in one thing. Let's just see
if we've got um
more.
Um
no, I think we're good. They're they're
all very long and all very complicated.
So, thank you all so much, but I think
we're done with that. Um anything you'd
like to close on? any any note that um
like for me personally I' I'd like to
ask how how us as general public who
were not involved in all of this how how
we can protect ourselves and how we can
keep a positive
>> there are a couple of different ways
and and we have to do all of them
simultaneously the most important I
think is to is to force our elected
officials
>> to do what we want them to do
>> and that is to ensure that our rights
are protected
>> and what they promise what they promise
every time and then forget about
>> and then don't do it and then we should
throw them out.
>> Mhm.
>> Until we find somebody who will protect
our rights. Um but we also have to we
have to speak and march and write
>> and take to the streets when that's
necessary and stand up for our rights
>> because otherwise our government
won't accomplish anything at all.
>> Yeah. Chucked out of social media.
Everything is there. I mean, I think
we've all had it. I've had it where just
like I was thrown out of everything for
a couple of weeks
>> because Mark Zuckerberg doesn't like
your opinions on things.
>> Yeah.
>> I got suspended from Facebook. Listen to
how stupid this is. I was dating a
Brazilian diplomat
>> and she sent me a video of of a zipline
>> in Bra in Brazil. You start at the top
of the mountain
>> and you go like, you know,
>> a kilometer on this thing.
>> And I responded, crazy Brazilians.
>> And I was suspended for hate speech
against Brazilians.
>> I mean, come on. We were just saying now
at the beginning of this podcast how
people use the word crazy just like even
as a compliment. Yeah.
>> You know, it was like that's a bit
crazy. It's out of the norm. Out of my
norm. That's crazy. on on X
um Disney posted that they were bringing
to Disney Plus a multi-part animated
series on the life of Mustafa Kamal
Adaturk.
I have 220 something thousand followers
and I wrote very disappointed that
Disney Plus would dedicate resources to
covering the life and times of a
genocidal maniac. Mhm.
>> The next thing I know, I get an email
from the German National Police
saying that they had just finished their
investigation of my alleged hate crime
against the Turkish people and they
decided that I had not committed a
crime.
And I was like, "Fuck you." Germans and
Turks both
tried to trample my freedom of speech.
I just can't believe how people are
being cancelled left, right, and
centers, losing jobs, everything just
for voicing opinions. They're not going
out shooting anyone. They're not holding
weapons. They're just sharing an
opinion.
>> At my last podcast, I had a uh sound
engineer. Great guy. Robbie West. Love
Robbie.
>> He and I disagree on immigration.
>> I'm a supporter of immigration. I'm from
an immigrant family. It would be ironic.
if you did.
>> Exactly.
>> And many of the members of my family
went to the United States as what are
called illegal immigrants. I hate that
term.
>> Yeah.
>> Undocumented immigrants is what I say.
>> Robbie wants to just close the borders,
seal them, and expel everybody who's not
there with paperwork.
>> Right. He's a he's an absolutist.
>> Okay, we disagree on that one issue.
He's a great guy. I I know his wife and
his kids. They're lovely people.
>> He mentioned offhandedly one time that
he worked in a hospital in Callispel,
Montana,
and somebody called every hospital in
Callispel, Montana until they found the
one that he worked in, and they
complained so viciferously that he was
fired from his job. Like, was that
really necessary? Does it make your life
better that that Robbie West doesn't
have a job anymore
>> because you don't like his position on
immigration?
>> That's that's how things have turned in
the United States. It's all very angry.
>> We're seeing it all the time. I mean, so
many actors out of work and they've been
told, "You're never going to work
again."
>> Yeah.
>> Um it's and and and you'll never know.
Kevin Spacy was just here. Just ate here
at our restaurant.
>> Fantastic. always loved him.
>> Yeah. And um yeah, that's it. He was
told, "That's it. You're out."
>> While he was here, I mean, I was meeting
him and he was having to go off and talk
to Netflix because they still they sued
him for the loss of revenue after firing
him.
>> I mean, it's it's really it's I find it
really scary. I really do. I'm quite
happy that I'm in my little rock.
>> Yeah.
>> In Cyprus, dealing with hotels and
hospitality.
Um, but yeah,
>> you know, I've actually reached out to
him a couple of times to ask him to come
on my podcast, Kevin Spacy.
>> I'll I'll put you in touch with his
manager.
>> Oh, thank you. I think I'd been emailing
the wrong people.
>> Yeah,
>> because I think he's been wronged.
>> I think so.
>> Yeah, we all do things in life that we
regret. Everybody does.
>> Everyone has done things.
>> But then the solution is to ruin the guy
so he never works again. Come on now.
>> Yeah. He lost his house. He lost
everything.
>> He did. He lost his house. It went to
auction.
>> Yep. He lost everything. Yeah.
Yeah. He was uh staying in the UK in an
Airbnb under code name.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> That's exactly right.
>> Yeah. Madness.
>> My dear, thank you so much. I will let
you get on with your day. I know that
you're going to the Cypress Diaspora
Forum for Lambbeese organizing that.
It's been fantastic to have you at San
Rafael.
>> I hope you come back many, many more
times.
>> Looking forward to it. It's a great
place and it's gigantic.
>> Thank you. It is big, isn't it? When
people come, they're like, "You run
this?" And I'm like, "Yeah, it's huge.
the gardens, the restaurants.
>> But I love it. I definitely get my steps
in working here in this environment.
It's like constant.
>> Excellent. Worth it.
>> I know. We're blessed, Tommy. When we
love what we do,
>> that's right. That's the point in life
to love what you do and then it never
feels like work.
>> You know, even at the CIA, I couldn't
wait to get to work in the morning.
>> Yeah.
>> I couldn't wait to see what I'd missed
during the night.
>> Yeah, absolutely.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, enjoy Cyprus. Thank you very much
>> and um always welcome.
>> Good to talk to you.
>> Thank you.